C – printf and scanf
Prev
Next

    printf() and scanf() functions are inbuilt library functions in C which are available in C library by default. These functions are declared and related macros are defined in “stdio.h” which is a header file.
    We have to include “stdio.h” file as shown in below C program to make use of these printf() and scanf() library functions.

1. C printf() function:

    printf() function is used to print the “character, string, float, integer, octal and hexadecimal values” onto the output screen.
    We use printf() function with %d format specifier to display the value of an integer variable.
    Similarly %c is used to display character, %f for float variable, %s for string variable, %lf for double and %x for hexadecimal variable.
    To generate a newline,we use “\n” in C printf() statement.

Note:

    C language is case sensitive. For example, printf() and scanf() are different from Printf() and Scanf(). All characters in printf() and scanf() functions must be in lower case.

Example program for C printf() function:
#include <stdio.h>
int main()
{
char ch = ‘A’;
char str[20] = “fresh2refresh.com”;
float flt = 10.234;
int no = 150;
double dbl = 20.123456;
printf(“Character is %c \n”, ch);
printf(“String is %s \n” , str);
printf(“Float value is %f \n”, flt);
printf(“Integer value is %d\n” , no);
printf(“Double value is %lf \n”, dbl);
printf(“Octal value is %o \n”, no);
printf(“Hexadecimal value is %x \n”, no);
return 0;
}                                                                                                                                                                                                   .

Output:
Character is A
String is fresh2refresh.com
Float value is 10.234000
Integer value is 150
Double value is 20.123456
Octal value is 226
Hexadecimal value is 96                                                                                                                                                                   .

You can see the output with the same data which are placed within the double quotes of printf statement in the program except

    %d got replaced by value of an integer variable  (no),

    %c got replaced by value of a character variable  (ch),

    %f got replaced by value of a float variable  (flt),

    %lf got replaced by value of a double variable  (dbl),

    %s got replaced by value of a string variable  (str),

    %o got replaced by a octal value corresponding to integer variable  (no),

    %x got replaced by a hexadecimal value corresponding to integer variable

    \n got replaced by a newline.

2. C scanf() function:

    scanf() function is used to read character, string, numeric data from keyboard
    Consider below example program where user enters a character. This value is assigned to the variable “ch” and then displayed.

    Then, user enters a string and this value is assigned to the variable ”str” and then displayed.

Example program for printf() and scanf() functions in C:
#include <stdio.h>
int main()
{
char ch;
char str[100];
printf(“Enter any character \n”);
scanf(“%c”, &ch);
printf(“Entered character is %c \n”, ch);
printf(“Enter any string ( upto 100 character ) \n”);
scanf(“%s”, &str);
printf(“Entered string is %s \n”, str);
}                                                                                                                                                                                                    .

Output:

Enter any character
a
Entered character is a
Enter any string ( upto 100 character )
hai
Entered string is hai                                                                                                                                                                        .

    The format specifier %d is used in scanf() statement. So that, the value entered is received as an integer and %s for string.
    Ampersand is used before variable name “ch” in scanf() statement as &ch

























C – Data Types
PrevNext

    C data types are defined as the data storage format that a variable can store a data to perform a specific operation.
    Data types are used to define a variable before to use in a program.
    Size of variable, constant and array are determined by data types.

C – data types:

There are four data types in C language. They are,
S.no 	
Types
	
Data Types
1 	Basic data types 	int, char, float, double
2 	Enumeration data type 	enum
3 	Derived data type 	pointer, array, structure, union
4 	Void data type 	void
1. Basic data types in C:
1.1. Integer data type:

    Integer data type allows a variable to store numeric values.
    “int” keyword is used to refer integer data type.
    The storage size of int data type is 2 or 4 or 8 byte.
    It varies depend upon the processor in the CPU that we use.  If we are using 16 bit processor, 2 byte  (16 bit) of memory will be allocated for int data type.
    Like wise, 4 byte (32 bit) of memory for 32 bit processor and 8 byte (64 bit) of memory for 64 bit processor is allocated for int datatype.
    int (2 byte) can store values from -32,768 to +32,767
    int (4 byte) can store values from -2,147,483,648 to +2,147,483,647.
    If you want to use the integer value that crosses the above limit, you can go for “long int” and “long long int” for which the limits are very high.

Note:

    We can’t store decimal values using int data type.
    If we use int data type to store decimal values, decimal values will be truncated and we will get only whole number.
    In this case, float data type can be used to store decimal values in a variable.

1.2. Character data type:

    Character data type allows a variable to store only one character.
    Storage size of character data type is 1. We can store only one character using character data type.
    “char” keyword is used to refer character data type.
    For example, ‘A’ can be stored using char datatype. You can’t store more than one character using char data type.
    Please refer C – Strings topic to know how to store more than one characters in a variable.

1.3. Floating point data type:

Floating point data type consists of 2 types. They are,

    float
    double

1. float:

    Float data type allows a variable to store decimal values.
    Storage size of float data type is 4. This also varies depend upon the processor in the CPU as “int” data type.
    We can use up-to 6 digits after decimal using float data type.
    For example, 10.456789 can be stored in a variable using float data type.

2. double:

    Double data type is also same as float data type which allows up-to 10 digits after decimal.
    The range for double datatype is from 1E–37 to 1E+37.

1.3.1. sizeof() function in C:

sizeof() function is used to find the memory space allocated for each C data types.
#include <stdio.h>
#include <limits.h>
int main()
{
int a;
char b;
float c;
double d;
printf(“Storage size for int data type:%d \n”,sizeof(a));
printf(“Storage size for char data type:%d \n”,sizeof(b));
printf(“Storage size for float data type:%d \n”,sizeof(c));
printf(“Storage size for double data type:%d\n”,sizeof(d));
return 0;
}                                                                                                                                                                                                   .

Output:

Storage size for int data type:4
Storage size for char data type:1
Storage size for float data type:4
Storage size for double data type:8                                                                                                                                                 .
1.3.2. Modifiers in C:

    The amount of memory space to be allocated for a variable is derived by modifiers.
    Modifiers are prefixed with basic data types to modify (either increase or decrease) the amount of storage space allocated to a variable.
    For example, storage space for int data type is 4 byte for 32 bit processor. We can increase the range by using long int which is 8 byte. We can decrease the range by using short int which is 2 byte.

    There are 5 modifiers available in C language. They are,

    short
    long
    signed
    unsigned
    long long

    Below table gives the detail about the storage size of each C basic data type in 16 bit processor.
    Please keep in mind that storage size and range for int and float datatype will vary depend on the CPU processor (8,16, 32 and 64 bit)

S.No 	C Data types 	storage Size 	Range
1 	char 	1 	–127 to 127
2 	int 	2 	–32,767 to 32,767
3 	float 	4 	1E–37 to 1E+37 with six digits of precision
4 	double 	8 	1E–37 to 1E+37 with ten digits of precision
5 	long double 	10 	1E–37 to 1E+37 with ten digits of precision
6 	long int 	4 	–2,147,483,647 to 2,147,483,647
7 	short int 	2 	–32,767 to 32,767
8 	unsigned short int 	2 	0 to 65,535
9 	signed short int 	2 	–32,767 to 32,767
10 	long long int 	8 	–(2power(63) –1) to 2(power)63 –1
11 	signed long int 	4 	–2,147,483,647 to 2,147,483,647
12 	unsigned long int 	4 	0 to 4,294,967,295
13 	unsigned long long int 	8 	2(power)64 –1
2. Enumeration data type in C:

    Enumeration data type consists of named integer constants as a list.
    It start with 0 (zero) by default and value is incremented by 1 for the sequential identifiers in the list.

    Enum syntax in C:

enum identifier [optional{ enumerator-list }];

    Enum example in C: 

enum month { Jan, Feb, Mar }; or
/* Jan, Feb and Mar variables will be assigned to 0, 1 and 2 respectively by default */
enum month { Jan = 1, Feb, Mar };
/* Feb and Mar variables will be assigned to 2 and 3 respectively by default */
enum month { Jan = 20, Feb, Mar };
/* Jan is assigned to 20. Feb and Mar variables will be assigned to 21 and 22 respectively by default */

    The above enum functionality can also be implemented by “#define” preprocessor directive as given below. Above enum example is same as given below.

#define Jan 20;
#define Feb 21;
#define Mar 22;
C – enum example program:
#include <stdio.h>
int main()
{
enum MONTH { Jan = 0, Feb, Mar };
enum MONTH month = Mar;
if(month == 0)
printf(“Value of Jan”);
else if(month == 1)
printf(“Month is Feb”);
if(month == 2)
printf(“Month is Mar”);
}                                                                                                                                                                                                    .

Output:

Month is March                                                                                                                                                                                .
3. Derived data type in C:

    Array, pointer, structure and union are called derived data type in C language.
    To know more about derived data types, please visit “C – Array“ , “C – Pointer” , “C – Structure” and “C – Union” topics in this tutorial.

4. Void data type in C:

    Void is an empty data type that has no value.
    This can be used in functions and pointers.
    Please visit “C – Function” topic to know how to use void data type in function with simple call by value and call by reference example programs.












C – Tokens and keywords
 Prev
Next

     C tokens, Identifiers and Keywords are the basics in a C program. All are explained in this page with definition and simple example programs.
1. C tokens:

    C tokens are the basic buildings blocks in C language which are constructed together to write a C program.
    Each and every smallest individual units in a C program are known as C tokens.

    C tokens are of six types. They are,

    Keywords               (eg: int, while),
    Identifiers               (eg: main, total),
    Constants              (eg: 10, 20),
    Strings                    (eg: “total”, “hello”),
    Special symbols  (eg: (), {}),
    Operators              (eg: +, /,-,*)

C tokens example program:
int main()
{
int x, y, total;
x = 10, y = 20;
total = x + y;
Printf (“Total = %d \n”, total);
}                                                                                                                                                                                                   .

where,

    main – identifier
    {,}, (,) – delimiter
    int – keyword
    x, y, total – identifier
    main, {, }, (, ), int, x, y, total – tokens

    Do you know how to use C token in real time application programs? We have given simple real time application programs where C token is used. You can refer the below C programs to know how to use C token in real time program.
Real time application C programs for your reference:
1. C program example – Real time Calculator program
2. C program example – Real time Bank Application program
2. Identifiers in C language:

    Each program elements in a C program are given a name called identifiers.
    Names given to identify Variables, functions and arrays are examples for identifiers. eg. x is a name given to integer variable in above program.

Rules for constructing identifier name in C:

    First character should be an alphabet or underscore.
    Succeeding characters might be digits or letter.
    Punctuation and special characters aren’t allowed except underscore.
    Identifiers should not be keywords.

3. Keywords in C language:

    Keywords are pre-defined words in a C compiler.
    Each keyword is meant to perform a specific function in a C program.
    Since keywords are referred names for compiler, they can’t be used as variable name.

C language supports 32 keywords which are given below. Click on each keywords below for detail description and example programs.
auto
	
double
	
int
	
struct
	
const
	
float 
	
short
	
unsigned
break
	
else
	
long
	
switch
	
continue
	
 for
	
signed
	
void 
case
	
enum
	
register
	
typedef
	
default
	
goto
	
sizeof 
	
volatile 
char
	
extern
	
return
	
union
	
do 
	
 if
	
static 
	
while




































C – Constant
 PrevNext

    C Constants are also like normal variables. But, only difference is, their values can not be modified by the program once they are defined.
    Constants refer to fixed values. They are also called as literals
    Constants may be belonging to any of the data type.

    Syntax:

const data_type variable_name; (or) const data_type *variable_name;
Types of C constant:

    Integer constants
    Real or Floating point constants
    Octal & Hexadecimal constants
    Character constants
    String constants
    Backslash character constants

S.no 	
Constant type
	
data type
	
Example
1 	Integer constants 	int
unsigned int
long int
long long int 	53, 762, -478 etc 
5000u, 1000U etc
483,647
2,147,483,680
2 	Real or Floating point constants 	float
doule 	10.456789
600.123456789
3 	Octal constant 	int 	013          /* starts with 0  */
4 	Hexadecimal constant 	int 	0×90        /* starts with 0x */
5 	character constants 	
 char
	‘A’   ,   ‘B’,     ‘C’
6 	string constants 	
char
	“ABCD”   ,   “Hai”
Rules for constructing C constant:
1. Integer Constants in C:

    An integer constant must have at least one digit.
    It must not have a decimal point.
    It can either be positive or negative.
    No commas or blanks are allowed within an integer constant.
    If no sign precedes an integer constant, it is assumed to be positive.
    The allowable range for integer constants is -32768 to 32767.

2. Real constants in C:

    A real constant must have at least one digit
    It must have a decimal point
    It could be either positive or negative
    If no sign precedes an integer constant, it is assumed to be positive.
    No commas or blanks are allowed within a real constant.

3. Character and string constants in C:

    A character constant is a single alphabet, a single digit or a single special symbol enclosed within single quotes.
    The maximum length of a character constant is 1 character.
    String constants are  enclosed within double quotes.

4. Backslash Character Constants in C:

    There are some characters which have special meaning in C language.
    They should be preceded by backslash symbol to make use of special function of them.
    Given below is the list of special characters and their purpose.

Backslash_character 	Meaning
\b 	Backspace
\f 	Form feed
\n 	New line
\r 	Carriage return
\t 	Horizontal tab
\” 	Double quote
\’ 	Single quote
\\ 	Backslash
\v 	Vertical tab
\a 	Alert or bell
\? 	Question mark
\N 	Octal constant (N is an octal constant)
\XN 	Hexadecimal constant (N – hex.dcml cnst)
How to use constants in a C program?

    We can define constants in a C program in the following ways.

    By “const” keyword
    By “#define” preprocessor directive

    Please note that when you try to change constant values after defining in C program, it will through error.

1. Example program using const keyword in C:

#include <stdio.h>

void main()
{
const int height = 100;             /*int constant*/
const float number = 3.14;   /*Real constant*/
const char letter = ‘A’;           /*char constant*/
const char letter_sequence[10] = “ABC”;           /*string constant*/
const char backslash_char = ‘\?’;                          /*special char cnst*/
printf(“value of height :%d \n”, height );
printf(“value of number : %f \n”, number );
printf(“value of letter : %c \n”, letter );
printf(“value of letter_sequence : %s \n”, letter_sequence);
printf(“value of backslash_char : %c \n”, backslash_char);
}
Output:
value of height : 100
value of number : 3.140000
value of letter : A
value of letter_sequence : ABC
value of backslash_char : ? 
2. Example program using #define preprocessor directive in C:

#include <stdio.h>

#define height 100
#define number 3.14
#define letter ‘A’
#define letter_sequence “ABC”
#define backslash_char ‘\?’
void main()
{
printf(“value of height : %d \n”, height );
printf(“value of number : %f \n”, number );
printf(“value of letter : %c \n”, letter );
printf(“value of letter_sequence : %s \n”,letter_sequence);
printf(“value of backslash_char : %c \n”,backslash_char);
}
Output:
value of height : 100
value of number : 3.140000
value of letter : A
value of letter_sequence : ABC
value of backslash_char : ?















C – Variable
 
Prev
Next

 

    C variable is a named location in a memory where a program can manipulate the data. This location is used to hold the value of the variable.
    The value of the C variable may get change in the program.
    C variable might be belonging to any of the data type like int, float, char etc.

Rules for naming C variable:

    Variable name must begin with letter or underscore.
    Variables are case sensitive
    They can be constructed with digits, letters.
    No special symbols are allowed other than underscore.
    sum, height, _value are some examples for variable name

Declaring & initializing C variable:

    Variables should be declared in the C program before to use.
    Memory space is not allocated for a variable while declaration. It happens only on variable definition.
    Variable initialization means assigning a value to the variable.

S.No
	
 Type 
	
Syntax
	
Example
1
	
Variable declaration
	
data_type variable_name;
	
int x, y, z; char flat, ch;
2
	
Variable initialization
	
data_type variable_name = value;
	
int x = 50, y = 30; char flag = ‘x’, ch=’l’;
There are three types of variables in C program They are,

    Local variable
    Global variable
    Environment variable

1. Example program for local variable in C:

    The scope of local variables will be within the function only.
    These variables are declared within the function and can’t be accessed outside the function.
    In the below example, m and n variables are having scope within the main function only. These are not visible to test function.
    Like wise, a and b variables are having scope within the test function only. These are not visible to main function.

#include<stdio.h>

void test();
int main()
{
int m = 22, n = 44;
// m, n are local variables of main function
/*m and n variables are having scope
within this main function only.
These are not visible to test funtion.*/
/* If you try to access a and b in this function,
you will get ‘a’ undeclared and ‘b’ undeclared error */
printf(“\nvalues : m = %d and n = %d”, m, n);
test();
}
void test()
{
int a = 50, b = 80;
// a, b are local variables of test function
/*a and b variables are having scope
within this test function only.
These are not visible to main function.*/
/* If you try to access m and n in this function,
you will get ‘m’ undeclared and ‘n’ undeclared
error */printf(“\nvalues : a = %d and b = %d”, a, b);
}
Output:
values : m = 22 and n = 44
values : a = 50 and b = 80
2. Example program for global variable in C:

    The scope of global variables will be throughout the program. These variables can be accessed from anywhere in the program.
    This variable is defined outside the main function. So that, this variable is visible to main function and all other sub functions.

#include<stdio.h>

void test();int m = 22, n = 44;
int a = 50, b = 80;
int main()
{
printf(“All variables are accessed from main function”);
printf(“\nvalues: m=%d:n=%d:a=%d:b=%d”, m,n,a,b);
test();
}
void test()
{
printf(“\n\nAll variables are accessed from” \
” test function”);
printf(“\nvalues: m=%d:n=%d:a=%d:b=%d”, m,n,a,b);
}
Output:

All variables are accessed from main function
values : m = 22 : n = 44 : a = 50 : b = 80

All variables are accessed from test function
values : m = 22 : n = 44 : a = 50 : b = 80
3. Environment variables in C:

    Environment variable is a variable that will be available for all C  applications and C programs.
    We can access these variables from anywhere in a C program without declaring and initializing in an application or C program.
    The inbuilt functions which are used to access, modify and set these environment variables are called environment functions.

    There are 3 functions which are used to access, modify and assign an environment variable in C. They are,

1. setenv()
2. getenv()
3. putenv()
Example program for getenv() function in C:

      This function gets the current value of the environment variable. Let us assume that environment variable DIR is assigned to “/usr/bin/test/”.

#include <stdio.h>
#include <stdlib.h>

int main()
{
printf(“Directory = %s\n”,getenv(“DIR”));
return 0;
}
Output:
/usr/bin/test/
 Example program for setenv() function in C:

      This function sets the value for environment variable. Let us assume that environment variable “FILE” is to be assigned “/usr/bin/example.c”

#include <stdio.h>
#include <stdlib.h>

int main()
{
setenv(“FILE”, “/usr/bin/example.c”,50);
printf(“File = %s\n”, getenv(“FILE”));
return 0;
}
Output:
File = /usr/bin/example.c
Example program for putenv() function in C:

      This function modifies the value for environment variable. Below example program shows that how to modify an existing environment variable value.

#include <stdio.h>
#include <stdlib.h>

int main()
{
setenv(“DIR”, “/usr/bin/example/”,50);
printf(“Directory name before modifying = ” \
“%s\n”, getenv(“DIR”));
putenv(“DIR=/usr/home/”);
printf(“Directory name after modifying = ” \
“%s\n”, getenv(“DIR”));
return 0;
}
Output:
Directory name before modifying = /usr/bin/example/
Directory name after modifying = /usr/home/
Difference between variable declaration & definition in C:
 S.no 
	
 Variable declaration
	
Variable definition
1
	
Declaration tells the compiler about data type and size of the variable.
	
Definition allocates memory for the variable.
2
	
Variable can be declared many times in a program.
	
It can happen only one time for a variable in a program.
3
	
The assignment of properties and identification to a variable.
	
Assignments of storage space to a variable.
















C – Operators and Expressions
 
PrevNext


    The symbols which are used to perform logical and mathematical operations in a C program are called C operators.
    These C operators join individual constants and variables to form expressions.
    Operators, functions, constants and variables are combined together to form expressions.
    Consider the expression A + B * 5. where, +, * are operators, A, B  are variables, 5 is constant and A + B * 5 is an expression.

Types of C operators:

C language offers many types of operators. They are,

    Arithmetic operators
    Assignment operators
    Relational operators
    Logical operators
    Bit wise operators
    Conditional operators (ternary operators)
    Increment/decrement operators
    Special operators

 Continue on types of C operators:

    Click on each operators name below for detail description and example programs.

S.no
	
Types of Operators
	
             Description              
1
	Arithmetic_operators 	These are used to perform mathematical calculations like addition, subtraction, multiplication, division and modulus
2
	Assignment_operators 	These are used to assign the values for the variables in C programs.
3
	Relational operators 	These operators are used to compare the value of two variables.
4
	Logical operators 	These operators are used to perform logical operations on the given two variables.
5
	Bit wise operators 	These operators are used to perform bit operations on given two variables.
6
	Conditional (ternary) operators 	Conditional operators return one value if condition is true and returns another value is condition is false.
7
	Increment/decrement operators 	These operators are used to either increase or decrease the value of the variable by one.
8
	Special operators 	&, *, sizeof( ) and ternary operators.

























C – Decision Control statement
PrevNext


    In decision control statements (C if else and nested if), group of statements are executed when condition is true.  If condition is false, then else part statements are executed.
    There are 3 types of decision making control statements in C language. They are,

      if statements
      if else statements
      nested if statements

“If”, “else” and “nested if” decision control statements in C:

    Syntax for each C decision control statements are given in below table with description.

Decision control statements 	Syntax 	Description
if 	if (condition) 
{ Statements; } 	In these type of statements, if condition is true, then respective block of code is executed.
if…else 	if (condition) 
{ Statement1; Statement2; }
else 
{ Statement3; Statement4; } 	In these type of statements, group of statements are executed when condition is true.  If condition is false, then else part statements are executed.
nested if 	if (condition1){ Statement1; }
else_if(condition2) 
{ Statement2; }
else Statement 3; 	If condition 1 is false, then condition 2 is checked and statements are executed if it is true. If condition 2 also gets failure, then else part is executed.
Example program for if statement in C:

      In “if” control statement, respective block of code is executed when condition is true.

int main()
{
  int m=40,n=40;
  if (m == n)
  {
  printf("m and n are equal");
  }
}

Output:
m and n are equal
Example program for if else statement in C:

      In C if else control statement, group of statements are executed when condition is true.  If condition is false, then else part statements are executed.

#include <stdio.h>
int main()
{
  int m=40,n=20;
  if (m == n) 
  {
  printf("m and n are equal");
  }
  else 
  {
  printf("m and n are not equal");
  }

}

Output:
m and n are not equal
Example program for nested if statement in C: 

    In “nested if” control statement, if condition 1 is false, then condition 2 is checked and statements are executed if it is true. 
    If condition 2 also gets failure, then else part is executed.

#include <stdio.h>
int main()
{
  int m=40,n=20;
  if (m>n) {
 printf("m is greater than n");
  }
  else if(m<n) {
  printf("m is less than n");
  }
  else {
  printf("m is equal to n");
  }
}

 Output:
m is greater than n


PrevNext

Share this C programming language with your friends
ss















C – Loop control statements
PrevNext


      Loop control statements in C are used to perform looping operations until the given condition is true. Control comes out of the loop statements once condition becomes false.
Types of loop control statements in C:

There are 3 types of loop control statements in C language. They are,

    for
    while
    do-while

    Syntax for each C loop control statements are given in below table with description.

S.no 	
Loop Name
	
Syntax
	
Description
1 	for 	for (exp1; exp2; expr3)
{ statements; } 	Where,
exp1 – variable initialization
( Example: i=0, j=2, k=3 )
exp2 – condition checking
( Example: i>5, j<3, k=3 )
exp3 – increment/decrement
( Example: ++i, j–, ++k )
2 	

while

	while (condition)
{ statements; } 	where, 
condition might be a>5, i<10
3 	

do while
	do { statements; }
while (condition); 	where,
condition might be a>5, i<10
Example program (for loop) in C:

      In for loop control statement, loop is executed until condition becomes false.

#include <stdio.h>

int main()
{
  int i;

  for(i=0;i<10;i++)
  {
      printf("%d ",i);
  }    

}

Output:
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
Example program (while loop) in C:

      In while loop control statement, loop is executed until condition becomes false.

#include <stdio.h>

int main()
{
  int i=3;

  while(i<10)
  {
 printf("%d\n",i);
 i++;
  }    

}

Output:
3 4 5 6 7 8 9
Example program (do while loop) in C:

      In do..while loop control statement, while loop is executed irrespective of the condition for first time. Then 2nd time onwards, loop is executed until condition becomes false.

#include <stdio.h>

int main()
{
  int i=1;

  do
  {  
   printf("Value of i is %d\n",i);
  i++;
  }while(i<=4 && i>=2);    

}

Output:
Value of i is 1
Value of i is 2
Value of i is 3
Value of i is 4
Difference between while & do while loops in C:
S.no 	
while
	
do while
1 	Loop is executed only when condition is true. 	Loop is executed for first time irrespective of the condition. After executing while loop for first time, then condition is checked.




PrevNext

Share this C programming language with your friends
	

fresh2r
















C – Case control statements
PrevNext


     The statements which are used to execute only specific block of statements in a series of blocks are called case control statements.

There are 4 types of case control statements in C language. They are,

    switch
    break
    continue
    goto

1. switch case statement in C:

    Switch case statements are used to execute only specific case statements based on the switch expression.
    Below is the syntax for switch case statement.

switch (expression)
{
case label1:   statements;
break;
case label2:   statements;
break;
default:    statements;
break;
}
Example program for switch..case statement in C:

#include <stdio.h>

int main ()
{
int value = 3;
switch(value)
{
case 1:
printf(“Value is 1 \n” );
break;
case 2:
printf(“Value is 2 \n” );
break;
case 3:
printf(“Value is 3 \n” );
break;
case 4:
printf(“Value is 4 \n” );
break;
default :
printf(“Value is other than 1,2,3,4 \n” );
}
return 0;
}
Output:
Value is 3
2. break statement in C:

    Break statement is used to terminate the while loops, switch case loops and for loops from the subsequent execution.
    Syntax: break;

Example program for break statement in C:

#include <stdio.h>

int main()
{
int i;

for(i=0;i<10;i++)
{
if(i==5)
{
printf(“\nComing out of for loop when i = 5″);
break;
}
printf(“%d “,i);
}
}
Output:
0 1 2 3 4
Coming out of for loop when i = 5
3. Continue statement in C:

    Continue statement is used to continue the next iteration of for loop, while loop and do-while loops.  So, the remaining statements are skipped within the loop for that particular iteration.
    Syntax : continue;

Example program for continue statement in C:

#include <stdio.h>

int main()
{
int i;
for(i=0;i<10;i++)
{
if(i==5 || i==6)
{
printf(“\nSkipping %d from display using ” \
“continue statement \n”,i);
continue;
}
printf(“%d “,i);
}
}
Output:
0 1 2 3 4
Skipping 5 from display using continue statement
Skipping 6 from display using continue statement
7 8 9
4. goto statement in C:

    goto statements is used to transfer the normal flow of a program to the specified label in the program.
    Below is the syntax for goto statement in C.

{
         …….
         go to label;
         …….
         …….
         LABEL:
         statements;
}
Example program for goto statement in C:

#include <stdio.h>

int main()
{
int i;
for(i=0;i<10;i++)
{
if(i==5)
{
printf(“\nWe are using goto statement when i = 5″);
goto HAI;
}
printf(“%d “,i);
}
HAI : printf(“\nNow, we are inside label name \”hai\” \n”);
}
 Output:
0 1 2 3 4
We are using goto statement when i = 5
Now, we are inside label name “hai”

















C – Type Qualifiers
PrevNext


    C – type qualifiers : The keywords which are used to modify the properties of a variable are called type qualifiers.

Types of C type qualifiers:

There are two types of qualifiers available in C language. They are,

    const
    volatile

1. const keyword:

    Constants are also like normal variables. But, only difference is, their values can’t be modified by the program once they are defined.
    They refer to fixed values. They are also called as literals.
    They may be belonging to any of the data type.

    Syntax: 

const data_type variable_name; (or) const data_type *variable_name;

    Please refer C – Constants topic in this tutorial for more details on const keyword.

2. volatile keyword:

    When a variable is defined as volatile, the program may not change the value of the variable explicitly.
    But, these variable values might keep on changing without any explicit assignment by the program. These types of qualifiers are called volatile.
    For example, if global variable’s address is passed to clock routine of the operating system to store the system time, the value in this address keep on changing without any assignment by the program. These variables are named as volatile variable.

    Syntax:       

volatile data_type variable_name; (or) volatile data_type *variable_name;

 


 